Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. We're
continuing on our CDC 6504 emulator. And now
we're going to load our most complex sample.
So let's
take a look at its assembly language. here
we have it. And let's move it over here. And
let's
move it up so we see all of the
instructions. There we go. We can just
barely see all the
instructions. This is our first thing that's
so long that we're going to end up in the
second
column of the instructions. So to start at
what we've got here, we got a data pseudo
operation
that fills the data memory with the string
hello E l with H being uppercase already and
E l. When
we're done, we want all these characters to
be upper uppercase. And so we're going to
write
a loop that's going to go through from zero
until it's and it's going to stop at a zero
bite and it's going to load the value, check
if it's already uppercase. If it's not, it's
going to subtract 20 to it, which we did
before because that's the mapping between
uppercase and
lowercase. And we're going to store it back
in. So we're done. 48 won't change because
that's already
uppercase. 65 will become 45. 65 6 C will
become 4C, etc. And then it'll stop and
it'll print out
the uppercase. So this is just a an
uppercase method in Python or whatever.
Okay. So
let's take a look at the code. We have a top
of a loop and we have a jump to the top of
the loop
at the bottom. This is a we're using x as
our iteration variable x because we have
this
really cool load that says I want to load
from zero offset by the current value in x.
Okay,
so x is going to start at zero because we're
going to clear it and then we're going to
add we're
going to slowly but surely add x. So this is
x= x + one each time through the loop. So
this
is the bottom of the loop, the continue area
where we're saying x++ or x= x+1 to advance
x through the string because we're going to
use x as the array offset as it's going
through our
little array. So we're going to load it.
We're going to load the value offset by x.
And then
we're going to immediately check to see if
we got a zero bite. And that's how we
terminate this loop
when we hit a zero bite. So we only want to
go through memory until we hit a zero bite.
Okay? So,
we don't want to run out of memory or blow
up or run into something else. We stop at a
zero
bite. And then we're going to check to see
if the letter we just got is already
uppercase. If it is,
that means it's less than lowercase a.
That's how ASKI works, right? So, let me go
ahead
and show you the ASI stuff. So if you look
at ASI you find that all the uppercase
characters
the lowercase characters are higher by a
factor of 20 hex. So a lowercase a is 61 and
uppercase
a is 41. You subtract 0x20 to get from
lowerase to upper. And our code is going to
upper. So,
we're checking to see if we are above or
below lowercase A. And if we're if
we're below lowerase I A already, we're
going to do a branch minus down here and
then increment to go to the next one. If on
the other hand, we are
above the letter A, then we're going to
subtract 20 and then we're going to store
that using our in index again as X. So x is
really cool. It's just going to be our
counter. And so this register is the
iteration variable. Well,
it is the iteration variable of our loop. So
let's go ahead and and get started. So
we'll turn on narration of execution. Line
ourselves up here. Take our first step.
Clear
the X register. PC0 X register. So now we're
at the top of the loop and we're going to do
a load from in memory location zero offset
by X register. So that the X register is
actually part
of this instruction. Okay. So let's go ahead
and load that PC01 accumulator from address
with X. Okay. So now you see that the
accumulator 0x48 and that is the uppercase
hello. And so the
next thing we're going to do and and that
load set the Z flag and the N flag and it's
neither
zero nor negative. And so let's go ahead and
run the if test to see if we're done with
the loop.
exit of the loop, but it didn't because
we're not we're not minus yet. And so that
was our that's
our top tested loop. And now what we're
going to do is we're gonna say if this is
greater than a if
it's if it's a or if it's less than a, we're
going to skip these next two lines. And the
next two
lines are a subtract of 0x20 and then an
indexed store into memory locations zero
offset by x. But
x is still position zero. So that is so this
is the letter H and it is already uppercase.
So we're
going to skip around this subtraction
calculation PC05 compare accumulator with
immediate 0x61
and now we're going to branch because it is
N. So
we're going to branch F minus. That means
we're already uppercase PCR
minus address. So it went to 0x0 D which
skipped around the subtraction. And now
we're at the
continue or the loop bottom the increment
part of the loop. And we're going to add one
to X
PC increment X register PC jump to address
one. Oh, I I I it went and did it
automatically. So,
we went up to the top of the loop and I
didn't catch it fast enough. So, it already
went and
X is now one. So, it's loading memory
location one into the accumulator. Okay. And
so the accumulator
now is nonzero. So we're we're going to
check to see if the loop is done. PC3 branch
equal address
0x10. And it didn't. So now we're going to
check to see the case of our current
character PC06.
So that is checking to see if it's above or
below a. and this one is above A and so
we're going to have to map it into
uppercase. So you'll notice that this this
BMI does not jump to
the c label. This one falls through PC 0x07
ifus address 0x0. So now we're at 0x09 not
0x0D. And
now we're going to do the subtract of 20 and
then we're going to store it into the
memory.
PC0x09 subtract with carry immediate 0x20
and now we're going to store it PC0 store
accumulator to address zero and X so so now
in location one we took this 45 that was our
calculated uppercase character and now it
has been stored in position one and so the
next
thing we do is add one and and jump to the
top of the loop. PC 0 increment x register
PC jump
to address one. So now we're at the top of
the loop. We're going to grab the next
instru the
next character because x is now two. So
we're going to grab this the the two offset
from our
array. PC01 load accumulator from address.
So we got 60. So, I'm going to just run this
a bit,
okay? And I'll try to stop it so that I can
show you the last iteration of the loop. So,
we'll watch X I'll probably try to catch it
while X sub the fourth iteration the
well the fifth iteration but sub4 is
running. Let's see if I can start it and
then catch it.
PC0x03 branch if equal address 0x10 PC 0x05
compare accumulator with immediate 0x61 PC
0x07
branch if minus address 0x0 we're on a
series of things that have to be converted
to uppercase
now PC store accumulator to address zero
index with X PC 0x0 D increment X register
PC0 X0 E jump
to address one PC 0x01 Load the accumulator
from address 0 and X with X PC 0x03 branch
if equal
address 0x10 PC 0x05 compare a cumulator
with immediate 0x61 PC 0x07 7 branch if
minus address
0x0 B PC 0x09 subtract with carry immediate
0x20 PC 0x0 B store accumulator to address
zero
index with X PC 0x0 D increment X register
PC0 X0E jump to address one PC 0x01 Lation
X PC 0x03 branch if equal address 0x10 PC
0x05 compare a cumulator with immediate 0x61
PC 0x07
branch if minus address 0x0 PC 0x0 Okay, so
I stopped it. So where are we at here?
We're about to store this last character. We
got it subtracted. So it's it's now
uppercase
and we're about to store it into position
offset by X and X. Our inoc our iteration
variable is four PC store accumulator to
address Z and X with X. The next thing we're
going to do
is increment X and so X is going to become
five. PC0X0 D increment X register. And now
we're going to jump to the top of the loop.
PC0 X0 E jump to address one. So now we're
at
the top of the loop. So X is five and we're
going to load the character at offset five.
And so now you'll notice as soon as we do
this accumulator is going to be zero and the
Z flag
is going to be set. PC0x01 load accumulator
from address z. So C got accumulator of zero
and we got Z. So now we will do a BEQ to
done. So we're going to jump right out of
this loop because now we've hit the zero
bite in our character array. PC03 branch if
address 0x10.
One more. PC0 break printed output. Hello.
So, it finished. It finished. And look,
it printed out an uppercase version of the
word hello. So, I recommend that you go in
and you
play with this and you load this and you
control the reset, the narrate, the
stepping. You
see how I'm doing it. , it it I'll tell you,
I I know what I'm doing and it's really hard
to
read these things and that's why I think of
this from an assembly language perspective.
trying to figure out. It doesn't hurt to
hover over and say, "Oh, that's the compare
instruction and that is the letter A." And
you can hover over these things and learn
some
stuff about what each of the locations is.
But so this is a nice little bit of code
that is a
loop with an if test. It's got increments.
It's got a continue in it. And so it is,
, a non-trivial piece of code. the the
smallest non-trivial piece of code that
I could fit into this particular emulator on
a screen that's small enough that maybe
that you can see this on a mobile device.
So, I hope you found this useful. Cheers.